Okay, so we pick up with דף עז Daf Ayin-Zayin 77, and
we are gonna start from the משנה. Mishnah. So the משנה Mishnah
on ע"ו עמוד ב, Ayin-Vav Amud Bet, ואלו הן הנהרגים. ve-eilu hen
ha-harugin. So now we go to from we did סקילה skilah and
שריפה, sreifah, now on to הרג, hereg, which is death by the
sword.
הרוצח ואנשי עיר הנדחת, ha-rotzei-ach ve-anshei ir ha-nidachat, only two: the murderer
and the people of the עיר הנדחת, ir ha-nidachat, the whole city
that worships עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So now we're gonna spend the
next few משניות mishnayot focusing on the parameters of רציחה. retzichah. So
that's an interesting aspect of סנהדרין, sanhedrin, which is that places where
that you get some basic parameters of some עבירות aveirot defined where
elsewhere they would not be defined. So we had that before by
בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer u-moreh, and now we're going to have
it by רציחה. retzichah. So, הרוצח שהכה את רעהו, ha-rotzei-ach she-hikah et
rei-eihu, so רוצח שהכה את רעהו באבן
או בברזל, rotzei-ach she-hikah et rei-eihu be-even o ve-barzel, if he smote
somebody with either a stone or iron or something metal, so clearly
directly by, you know, either by wounding or by puncture, by stabbing.
כבשו עליו לתוך המים kevasho alav letoch ha-mayim או לתוך האש, o
letoch ha-esh, or held him underwater
or into a fire, ואינו יכול לעלות משם ve-eino yachol la'alot mi-sham
and prevented him from getting out of there, even though he didn't
actually put him into the water, ומת umet and he died, חייב,
chayav, he's liable. דחפו לתוך המים או לתוך האש, dechafo letoch ha-mayim
o letoch ha-esh, now somewhat ironically, if he actively pushed him into
the water or the fire, it's still, I mean obviously if he
cannot get out he would be חייב, chayav, obviously that's a קל
וחומר kal va-chomer from holding him there, but there's a case he'd
be פטור. patur.
Why? ויכול לעלות משם, ve-yachol la'alot mi-sham, if he had the ability
to get out from there from the moment of being pushed let's
say, ומת umet and something happened and he couldn't, פטור patur he'd
be exempt. Now that seems very bizarre, even though the guy was
trying to get himself out and nevertheless the guy who pushed him
in is exempt. But this gets to a general rule that we
like even if it's like a case of a stone, there's an
idea that it has to have a שיעור מיתה, shiur mitah, that
the stone or whatever that he was hit with, we have to
look at it and assess that it had the size and the
weight and whatever that under normal circumstances it could have killed him.
Otherwise we assume that what he did was not an act of
murder, he did an act of wounding and then something happened and
the guy died, and that was considered to be unexpected or freak,
but it wasn't that the act himself he did at the time
could have anticipated that it would have actually killed him. So the
same is true about this case about the fire and the water,
you know, push somebody in and somebody's able to swim, then the
act is not considered an act of murder even if something happens
to the guy and he all of a sudden gets a cramp,
or something unusual and he's not able to get out from there.
Okay. ושיסה בו את הכלב ve-shisah bo et ha-kelev ושיסה בו את
הנחש ve-shisah bo et ha-nachash פטור. patur. Let's say he sicked his
dog or the snake on him, he is exempt, because that is
considered גרמא, grama, even though he obviously is intending it or whatever,
he did not directly attack the person himself. He did it through
the agency of this dog and ultimately it was the dog who
was doing it. הכיש בו את הנחש, hikish bo et ha-nachash, let's
say he took a snake and directly put the fangs of the
snake into the person. רבי יהודה מחייב וחכמים פוטרין. Rabbi Yehuda mechayev
ve-chachamim potrin. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you're חייב chayav and חכמים
chachamim say you're exempt. Obviously רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position here seems
to make most sense because he is like directly doing it. So
we will see. But like we
know by נזק, nezek, by damages, causation is not enough. You need
a direct act of murder and directly you know through the person,
through the things that he is using to hit, to stab, to
hold the guy under the fire. Things that cause those things to
happen, that's not seen as the person's direct action even though it
definitely causes death. The person cannot be executed. You know the גמרא
Gemara often says פטור בדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים, patur b'dinei adam
ve-chayav b'dinei shamayim, that you're still liable in heaven. רמב"ם Rambam actually
calls such people רוצחים, rotzchim, they are murderers, but just murderers who
cannot be executed. Okay, but that's important that a part of what
we're doing here is defining exactly the parameters of what is considered
to be the person's action and direct action and cause act of
murder. So let's take a look. אמר שמואל מפני מה לא נאמר
יד בברזל? Amar Shmuel mipnei mah lo neemar yad be-varzel? When it
speaks about iron it does not say, by other things it says
אבן יד, even yad, a stone of the hand, or כלי עץ
יד, kli etz yad, a wooden thing that sits in the hand,
and from that idea like it's a handful we get the idea
that it has to have a שיעור, shiur, it has to be
big enough to actually
cause, weighty enough and so on and that's the idea that we
measure and determine at the moment whether this thing we anticipate could
cause death. But it doesn't say by
ברזל barzel כלי ברזל יד. kli barzel yad. It just says אם
בכלי ברזל. im b'kli barzel. So why doesn't it say יד? yad?
שהברזל ממית בכל שהוא, she-barzel meimit be-chol shiur, because a metal vessel
can actually kill even a small amount, there is no שיעור. shiur.
Now the גמרא Gemara says that the context makes a difference because
it says תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, רבי
אומר גלוי וידוע לפני מי שאמר והיה העולם שהברזל ממית בכל שהוא.
Rabbi omer galuy ve-yadu-ah lifnei mi she-amar ve-hayah ha-olam she-ha-barzel meimit be-chol
shiur. It's known before the one who said and the world was,
that iron
kills in any amount. even the smallest amount has the ability to
kill, but now the גמרא Gemara qualifies והני מילי דברזא מידזא. ve-hani
mili de-barza midza. That's only if you use it for cutting or
for puncturing, for stabbing. If you try to hit somebody with a
metal vessel then obviously you would have a שיעור shiur just like
a wooden one would. Okay, והכובש את חבירו לתוך המים. ve-hakovesh et
chavero le-toch ha-mayim. Now, the person is held underneath water. רישא רבותא
קמשמע לן וסיפא רבותא קמשמע לן. reisha revuta kamashma lan ve-seifa revuta
kamashma lan. The beginning tells us a חידוש chiddush and the end
is a חידוש. chiddush. רישא רבותא קמשמע לן, reisha revuta kamashma lan,
אף על גב דלאו איהו דחפו. af al gav de-lav ihu dechafo.
The first case that's considered an act of murder, it doesn't have
you pushing, this guy pushing being pushed into the water. The guy
was in the water anyway, he was going swimming, okay? So the
murderer did not push him, he just held him under the water.
כיון דאין יכול לעלות משם, keivan de-ein yachol la'alot misham, since he's—it's
impossible to get out and this person is holding him under, ומת
חייב, u-met chayav, that's considered an act of murder. We don't say
it's גרמא. gerama. You are under the water anyway, I was just
preventing you from getting out. The fact that I was preventing you
is considered to be holding you underwater and is considered an act
of murder.
סיפא רבותא קמשמע לן, seifa revuta kamashma lan, the end is a
חידוש, chiddush, אף
על גב דדחפו, af al gav de-dechafo, even if he actively pushed
him into the water or the fire, כיון דיכול לעלות משם, keivan
de-yachol la'alot misham, since it would be expected that he could get
out of there,
ומת פטור, u-met patur, he's exempt. Okay, so that's what we said
before, that the סיפא, seifa, the idea that you assess it based
on what could have been sort of what was seen as having—what
did it have the ability to do as being able to be
assessed at that moment, even if something unexpected happened. Now the question
also is like let's say he didn't know about something, like let's
say the guy had, I don't know, a leg cramp that the
murderer didn't know about, or you know, so anyway interesting ways of
trying to figure out exactly what it means that something happened or
what was it he could have—could have under what circumstances?
Let's say there was a, you know, let's say there was seaweed
under there that nobody knew about but the guy got his leg
caught in the seaweed. So again, how do you determine could have?
But anyway, that is the idea that the murderer has to—the act
has to be defined as an act of murder at the time
in terms of the ability to—to murder. But as we see by
holding the guy underwater, it doesn't—it can just be by preventing something
from happening, that is actually preventing him from getting out, that is
considered holding him, that is considered an active act. Okay, כבוש מנא
לן, kavush mana lan, where do you know that holding the guy
underwater is considered an act of murder? אמר שמואל דאמר קרא, amar
shmuel de-amar kra, because the verse says, או באיבה, o ve-eivah, or
with hatred. לרבות את המצמצם, lerabbot et ha-metzamtzem, so the extra word
או—you o know, why didn't it say באיבה be-eivah or somehow? That
tells you לרבות את המצמצם, lerabbot et ha-metzamtzem, that extra word tells
you that even this act of holding the guy is considered an
act of keeping the guy underwater, is an act of murder. ההוא
גברא
דמצמצמה לחיותא דחבריה בשמשא. hahu gavra de-metzamtzemah le-chayuta de-chavreih be-shimsha. Now, there
was a certain person that kept his—that took his friend's animal and
held it
under—not underwater, בשמשא, be-shimsha, so to prevent—kept it in the sun, prevented
it from getting shade, ומתה, u-metah, and it died of sunstroke.
So that should be just like the case of our משנה. mishna.
רבינא מחייב ורב אחא בריה דרבא פוטר. ravina mechayev ve-rav acha bereih
de-rava patur. רבינא ravina says you're חייב chayav and רב אחא בריה
דרבא rav acha bereih de-rava says you're exempt.
רבינא מחייב קל וחומר, ravina mechayev kal va-chomer, ומה רוצח שלא עשה
בו שוגג כמזיד ואונס כרצון. u-mah rotzeach she-lo asah bo shogeg ke-mezid
ve-ones ke-ratzon. By רוצח, rotzeach, it's a narrower category—meaning רוצח rotzeach obviously
is much—much more stringent, but it's a narrower category because it's more
stringent, punishable by death. It's a much more narrow category of who
we say actually has done an act of murder. So by רוצח,
rotzeach, we would never say that if somebody did it by accident
it was like they did it willingly, and שלא עשה בו שוגג
כמזיד ואונס כרצון—or she-lo asah bo shogeg ke-mezid ve-ones ke-ratzon unintentional like
intentional; חייבו הכתוב המצמצם, chiyevo ha-katuv ha-metzamtzem, nevertheless the תורה Torah says
holding somebody present, you know, keeping somebody in their place and preventing
them to escape something that's killing them is considered an act of
murder. נזיקין שעשה בהן שוגג כמזיד ואונס כרצון, nezikin she-asah bahen shogeg
ke-mezid ve-ones ke-ratzon, נזק nezek we know the תורה Torah is a
broader category, even though you need an act, you don't need intent.
Even somebody that's accidental, negligent, or even an אונס, ones, completely out
of their hands, when an אדם מועד לעולם. adam muad le-olam. So
it's much broader, you don't even need intent, so certainly the act
would be defined, you know, you wouldn't define the act more narrowly.
אינו דין שחייב בו המצמצם? eino din she-chayav bo ha-metzamtzem? So holding
someone in a position that causes—that doesn't let them free themselves, or
the animal, and then the animal dies, that is an act of
מזיק. mazzik. Makes a lot of sense. ורב אחא בר רבא פוטר,
ve-rav acha bar rava patur, but רב אחא בר רבא rav acha
bar rava says you're exempt. Why? אמר משרשיא מאי טעמא דהוא דאבא,
amar mesharshia mai ta'ama de-hu de-abba, what was the reason of my
father's father—which is his grandfather—דפטור? de-patur? אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse
says,
מות יומת המכה רוצח הוא. mot yumat ha-makeh rotzeach hu. He is
a murderer that הוא *hu* is saying this extra idea that even
holding a guy under water we’re going to say you’re חייב chayav.
*chayav*, that’s specifically by a murderer, בנזיקין לא חייב chayav ליה מצמצם
metzamtzem. *benzikin lo chayiv lei mitztamtzen*, not by נזיקין *nezikin*. I really
have to tell you that I don’t begin to understand this, why
it should be a narrow definition. I mean even like by a
public policy issue and you could sort of say, you know, we
want to punish murder and so on, besides that there’s all these
ways in which we exempt a murderer, you know, and we really
try like always to not use the death penalty. But we also
want to be want damages to go, you know, to be to
be punished. And since more broadly we’re ready to make somebody pay
for damages, it is very strange this opinion that מצמצם *mitztamtzen* is
exempt by נזיקין *nezikin*. Anyway, that is that position. Now תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafos* here, some of these large תוספותים *Tosafoses* here, which thankfully cut
the size of the דף *daf* into a into like a third,
are not really related to us, they’re really about נזיקין *nezikin* issues.
So for example, the first one is about the issue about is
it really true that אדם מועד לעולם *adam muad l’olam* or are
there cases in which an אדם *adam* is not מועד לעולם *muad
l’olam*, in which a person actually needs a certain degree of fault
or negligence or whatever. That’s a major issue of תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*
and רמב"ן *Ramban*, a major debate in many places in ש"ס *Shas*.
The next one is the issue about נזיקין מצמצם *nezikin mitztamtzen* and
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*’s general comparison to it seems like the general assumption
here is that if you’re חייב chayav, *chayav* for רוצח *rotzeach* you’re
going to be חייב Chayav, *chayav* for נזיקין *nezikin*, right, that’s the
first opinion, that certainly makes the most sense. And then trying to
raise questions based on certain סוגיות *sugyas* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
where it seems like it doesn’t fit with other things that we
know about נזיקין *nezikin*. But anyway, and then there’s an interesting thing
here about how he uses the idea of אש *eish*, which I’ll
get to, actually that’s the next תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*, I’ll get to
it later. Okay, but anyway those תוספותים *Tosafoses* are much more about
נזיקין *nezikin* issues. Let’s go back to our גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. אמר
רבא Amar Rava *Amar Rava*, says רבא Rava: *Rava*: כפתו ומת ברעב
פטור patur. *kafso u’meis b’ra’av patur*. If somebody bound somebody up and
let the guy starve to death, he’s exempt. Now how is that
different than holding the guy under water? Because the idea is is
that he’s not right now starving. Right now he is not, so
it’s like we’re going to see in a minute if you bound
somebody up and a fire was going to come or the sun
was going to come and so on, but you weren’t directly holding
the person in that place where that thing that is killing him
is already present, then it’s not like you killed him. It’s גרמא
grama. *grama*, like I said you might be a רוצח *rotzeach*, you
definitely caused his death, but to kill him means to directly do
an act that is basically, you know, like you’re holding him under
the water, you are drowning him. Here you’re binding him up and
then letting leaving him to die. All right, so that’s the difference
because he’s not in the middle of, you know, of this thing
that is killing him right now. כפתו ומת ברעב פטור Patur. *kafso
u’meis b’ra’av patur*, you’re exempt. ואמר רבא Va'amar Rava, *V’amar Rava*, and
רבא Rava *Rava* also said: כפתו בחמה ומת בצינה ומת חייב Chayav,
*kafso b’chama u’meis b’tzina u’meis chayav*. If the guy was in the
sun or in cold and you bound him up you’re חייב chayav.
*chayav*. Now that’s actually a little different, right, because normally people can
be exposed to the sun and the cold for a while and
nothing happens to it. So even though the thing is already active,
like if a person will die from sunstroke or will die from,
you know, sun exposure or from exposure to the cold, at this
moment you don’t think that they’re in the process of being killed
or some killing thing, you know, something that is threatening their life
being on top of them. So, you know, but nevertheless we say
that that’s like holding the guy in the under the water, holding
the guy in the fire, that thing that eventually will kill them
is already on top of them and therefore you by holding and
ensuring and even though you don’t continue to hold, you bind them
up and you walk away, but you’ve sort of pushed them into
that thing in a way in which they can’t get out of
it, and that thing is going to kill them and that thing
was there right then. Like if you threw somebody into a, you
know, I don’t know, you locked the door on somebody and you
walked away, you’re not holding them when the fire kills them, but
you’ve you have kept them in a situation in which the killing
thing is present. Therefore and you and that is considered an act
of murder. Okay, you have done the act of murder and then
eventually the thing will overcome them and and take their life but
you’ve already done the act of murder. But the thing has to
the active thing that’s going to kill them has to be present.
Okay, and that’s the difference between these cases. Now as gets also
clarified by the next line. ואמר רבא Va'amar Rava, *V’amar Rava*, רבא
Rava *Rava* also said: סוף חמה לבוא sof chama lavo סוף צינה
לבוא
*sof chama lavo sof tzina lavo*, let’s say you tie them up
and it was a nice beautiful cool day
and, you know, or was nighttime even whatever, but you knew that
the sun was going to come out and by the time the
sun came out the person was left in that sun, they would
die from heat exposure. Or the same by the cold, right now
the weather you could stay there for a year and you’d be
fine, but, you know, a big cold frost is about to hit
and you knew that. And you tied the person up and left
them there. Since the cold was not currently present, that same coldness
that was sort of going to kill them as it continued, so
what you did is you left them to die but you did
not do an act of
killing. סוף חמה *Sof chama*... If you bind somebody up in front
of a lion, you are פטור, Patur. in front of gnats and
on the gnats eat the person alive, you're חייב. chayav, Now what's
the difference between the two? So רש"י Rashi says by the lion
you could have run away anyway. That doesn't seem to fit what's
going on here. תוספות Tosafot says that it's the same issue we've
been talking about. The ארי ari is not currently eating the person.
So, you know, so that is seen as although the ארי ari
is present, it's not on top of the person.
And it's like, you know, binding somebody up and then a river's
going to come and wash the person away is not the same
as holding them underwater. Whereas the gnats, the person is right now
being attacked by mosquitoes and you're not letting the person escape. So
there the thing is on top, there is something even though it's
going to require a period of time, but holding the person in
that thing that he's going that is killing them or that, you
know, will continue will kill them, but they're already in that thing.
Now רב אשי Rav Ashi אמר, רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi, says,
אפילו לפני יתושים נמי פטור. afilu lifnei yetushim nami patur. Even in
front of gnats you're
exempt. Why? הני אזלי והני אתו hani azlei vehani atu because you
know it's not the same gnats. Like if you're in a swamp
or whatever, the current mosquitoes will leave and others will come. So
it's an interesting question like do you use it as a force
of nature, you know, and like it's just, you know, the ongoing
presence of mosquitoes or do you say no, each one is a
different thing. You know, you don't view the sun that each one
is a different sort of sunray that's coming at you. That's just
a continued thing. So that's a question of how to view this.
Okay. איתמר. itmar. It was taught. כפה. kafa. Now by the way,
this תוספות Tosafot of סוף חמה לבוא sof chama lavo. raises an
important question which he thinks that because there's a principle that אשו
משום חציו, isho mishum chitzo, that a fire is like your arrow,
that he first assumes that means that if somebody lights a fire
and it can be anticipated it will spread and it spreads and
kills somebody, that that person has done an act of רציחה retzicha
presumably because he was warned and he was intending to do it
and so on. As opposed to just directly applying the fire to
the person because he learns that from a בבא קמא Bava Kamma
discussion about by damages we say אשו משום חציו, isho mishum chitzo,
it's like your arrow, and there's a discussion there that תוספות Tosafot
understands tells you that you're חייב רציחה. chayav retzicha. Not everybody agrees
with that assumption. That's assumption number one. You light a fire and
you know it'll spread and it spreads even though it took the
wind to spread it or whatever, you knew that would happen, that's
רציחה. retzicha. But then תוספות Tosafot says oh if that's true, so
if when I do it and then it'll spread it's רציחה, retzicha,
if I put somebody in front of a fire is coming down,
right, and it'll take an hour for the fire to get to
this house but I lock somebody in this house, that's also רציחה
retzicha which is very strange because based on everything we've looked that's
a type of like a סוף חמה לבוא. You know the fire
isn't on top of him. But based on this idea that fire
is like your arrow and it's in the process, you know תוספות
Tosafot puts that in in complicated issues. But then תוספות Tosafos, steps
back and says you know what that's maybe not true and you
would not be חייב chayav for רציחה retzicha etc. So there's two
questions. A, by a fire when the fire continues but at least
I lit the fire, there you could see it's like an arrow
I shot and keeps on going. But then תוספות Tosafos, to assume
that if you put somebody a place and then a fire will
come that's also רציחה, retzicha, you know how's that different than this
case? So תוספות Tosafos has to say well this case the guy
was already standing in the sun and I just stopped him from
moving. Like or the guy who was already standing and I just
stopped him from moving. But if I bound somebody up and put
him outside and then eventually the sun was going to rise and
the sun would kill him, that would be like lighting a fire
and having the fire go kill him, which is again very, very
strange and in the end תוספות Tosafos steps away from that. So
the easiest thing to understand is bracket all that and assume we're
only talking about the case that the guy is already present in
the presence and the thing that is going to kill him is
on top of him. That would be a case that's considered an
act of murder. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now we have one more case amongst this
and it says the following.
כפה עליו גיגית ופרע עליו מעזיבה איתמר. kafa alav gigit upara alav
maaziva itmar. It was taught. כפה עליו גיגית, kafa alav gigit, you
put a barrel on top of somebody and they die basically out
of suffocation. ופרע עליו מעזיבה, upara alav maaziva, you tear the rooftop
away from somebody and they die because of exposure. רבה ורבי זירא.
Rava veRabbi Zeira. It's a debate now. חד אמר חייב
וחד אמר פטור. chad amar chayav vechad amar patur. One says חייב,
chayav. one says פטור. Patur. תסתיים דרבה הוא דאמר פטור. tistayeim deRava
hu deamar patur. Let us conclude that רבה Rava is the one
who says you're exempt. דאמר רבה כפתו ומת ברעב פטור, deamar רבה
kfato umet beraav patur, that if he dies in hunger you're exempt.
So here too it's going to be, he sort of sees this
like the hunger, it's not like you're in the sky standing in
the cold, you know, the somehow I guess
I don't get the guy by suffocating the guy in the barrel.
That sort of much more seems to be like the case that
the thing that's going to kill him is on top of him.
But at least the case of the cold is something where it's
considered to be that it's somehow it's going to come later. Maybe
right now it's not yet cold. It's again hard to understand. Are
we talking about it's on top of him or going to come
later? But the גמרא Gemara initially compares... compares it to something that's
gonna come later, like the hunger.
So it says, where were we? חסדא Chisda and רבה בר חנה
Rabbah bar Chana דאמרי d'amri פטור. Patur, ואדרבה, V'adaraba,
חסדא Chisda דרבי זירא d'Rabbi Zeira הוא דאמר hu d'amar פטור. patur,
No, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira is the one who says you're exempt.
דאמר D'amar רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira says: האי
מאן דאייל לחבריה בביתא דשישא, Hai man d'ayal l'chavrei b'vesa d'shisha, somebody
puts his friend into a marble house where, you know, like there
can be no, like it's, what do you say, like it's hermetically
sealed, okay, ואדליק ליה שרגא v'adlik lei sharga and lights a candle,
ומית חייב u'meit chayav and he dies, חייב, chayav. because presumably the
candle eats up the oxygen and that's like actively killing him, okay.
טעמא דאדליק ליה שרגא, Ta'ama d'adlik lei sharga, that's because he lit
the candle, that's seen as the act of murder. הלוא אדליק ליה
שרגא לא, Halo adlik lei sharga lo, if he didn't light the
candle, no, it wouldn't be, so you see and that's just like
this case here about putting him in the barrel, is putting him
in the house where eventually he'll die because of lack of oxygen,
all right, but it's not happening like right away. So אמרי, Amri,
no, התם בלא שרגא לא מטי הבלא בשעתיה, Hasam belo sharga lo
mati hevla b'shat'ei, there without the candle there was nothing problem right
now, you know, there's plenty of air in the house. The idea
that there's insufficient air doesn't start to become a problem until later.
So there the person was not in the middle of a process,
that's why in that case you'd be פטור. patur. But והכא, v'hacha,
but here, by the barrel case, בלא שרגא נמי מטי הבלא בשעתיה,
belo sharga nami mati hevla b'shat'ei, the lack of air starts immediately,
right, as soon as somebody's put in a barrel, upside down barrel
that is, okay, all of a sudden they feel this lack of
air. All right, so then again, if that's how we're describing it,
the cold has already begun, the lack of air, you know, when
you tear off the rooftop, the lack of air has already begun,
then what's the debate? Then everybody should say that you're חייב, chayav.
it should be like the case of the sun, you know, tying
somebody up in the sun, like what exactly makes this case different?
So if you look at תוספות, Tosafos this little תוספות, Tosafos he
says, כפה עליו גיגית, Kafa alav gigis, on the bottom of עין
זין עמוד א, Ayin Zayin amud Aleph, כפה עליו גיגית, Kafa alav
gigis, תוספות says, לא דמי לסוף חמה לבוא ולסוף צינה לבוא, lo
dami l'sof chama lavo u'l'sof tzina lavo, it's not like the thing
will eventually come, right, דהתם ליכא חמה וצינה כלל, d'hasam leika chama
v'tzina klal, it's not there at all, as opposed to this case
of course we said
where the גמרא Gemara, concludes there's already lack of sufficient air, ולא
מתחיל בהן בשעתו, v'lo matchil bahen b'sha'ato, it didn't
have yet begun. Okay, so then comparative case of the guy's tying
the guy up in the sun, ולא דמי לכפתו בחמה וצינה, v'lo
dami l'kasto b'chama v'tzina, דכבר אתו עליה מקודם חמה וצינה שיש בהן
כדי להמית. d'kvar asu alav mikodem chama v'tzina she'yesh bahen k'dei l'hamis.
There תוספות says it's like this sun is a sun that can
kill if you're left in it long enough, but it's the same
heat and the same cold, but if you're exposed to it long
enough, so it's the same thing. How's that different than this case?
אבל הכא ליכא אלא הולך ומתחזק עליו. Aval hacha leika ela holeich
u'mischazek alav. Okay,
here it's like the thing is getting worse, so it's, it also
gets worse in the sun, but presumably there it's just the same
heat over prolonged time, so there it's like that is something you
put them right in the killing thing, whereas presumably the case of
the barrel is, you know, you start with a certain amount of
oxygen, then gets less oxygen, then gets less oxygen, so the absence
of oxygen as it were grows, it's not like the same heat
over more time, somehow it's seen somewhat as the actual killing thing
is changing, the killing thing is the absence of oxygen and that's
growing to be more powerful. I don't get the case exactly of
ripping the rooftop off of the guy, maybe it's a case also
where it's not so cold to begin with and it gets colder,
although that hasn't been explained. Okay, and so anyway תוספות just ends
by saying ודמי לכפתו ברעב שכבר יש רעב מעט ותמיד מתחזק. v'dami
l'kasto b'ra'av she'kvar yesh ra'av m'at v'tamid mis'chazek.
Let's say the guy who you leave to starve to death was
already like, you know, it was after יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, was
already quite hungry, but not enough to kill the person. Okay, so
what would be that case, what's going to kill them again in
the eventually isn't the same hunger but it's a hunger that's going
to grow. So that's the way תוספות understands it. You hold somebody
in the thing that they is killing them with given enough time,
that's רציחה. retzicha. You hold them in it and then something else
is going to kill them from the situation they're in now, the
sun will rise or whatever, obviously that's not. You keep you hold
somebody in something which the problem will increase over time, it's not
the same thing, it's it'll become bigger and a bigger issue and
that's going to be what's going to kill them, that is this
debate here about the barrel and about the ripping of the rooftop
off of something.
Okay, so that's all the cases about מצמצם. Now we're going to
deal with cases not actively holding somebody over but like two step
things, like indirect, let's take a look. אמר amar,
רבא Rava says רבא: דחפו לבור וסולם
בבור, Dakfo l'bor v'sulam b'bor, you push guy into a well and
there's a ladder, so that act of pushing him into the well
isn't murder, there's a ladder, ובא אחר וסילקו, u'va acher v'silko, somebody
else comes and removes the ladder, ואפילו הוא קודם וסילקו, v'afillu hu
kodem v'silko, or let's say you, the guy who's the murderer, comes
and he removes the ladder, פטור, patur you're exempt, this is the
irony, right, that you can kill a guy and
get Why? דבעידנא דשדייה יכול לעלות, Dbe'idna deshadye yakhol le'alos,
the active act, the pushing in the בור bor was not an
act of murder. There was a- there was the ladder.
The removing of the ladder afterwards is not an active act, is
not like killing the person. It's just taking away the thing that's
going to let the person escape. So that's גרמא. grama? Now you
might say wait, why is that גרמא? grama. How is it different
than holding the guy under the water, right? You're like keeping the
guy in the בור. bor. But I could say one of two
things. Number one is that you didn't actually do something to the
guy, you just did something to the ladder, which raises an interesting
question. Really? So if a guy's in a house that's a burning
house and you lock the door and he can't get out, because
you didn't do something to the guy, that's not an act of
murder? You have to touch the guy? Like that's one definite possibility,
but that needs to be explored. The other possibility is not because
you didn't touch the guy, but because sort of like we were
talking about before, being in the well is not what kills him.
What kills him is the fact that he's going to die out
of starvation. And that's not something you're doing right now. That's something
that's going to come later. Okay, so two very different reasons why
removing the ladder would not be חייב. Okay, ואמר רבא, Ve-amar Rava,
רבא also said: זרק חץ ותריס בידו, Zarak chetz utris beyado,
shoot an arrow at a guy and the guy is holding a
shield. So the shooting of the arrow is not an act of
murder. ובא אחר ונטלו Uba acher venatlo and somebody comes and removes
the shield before the arrow gets to him, and then the arrow
gets him and kills him. ואפילו הוא קדם ונטלו, Ve'afilu hu kadam
venatlo, or even you, you're super fast or like let's say you
have a string and you pull the string away from the guy
and the guy- you pull the string and the shield yanks away
from the guy and the arrow goes and kills him. ובא אחר
ונטלו ואפילו הוא קדם ונטלו פטור, Uba acher venatlo ve'afilu hu kadam
venatlo patur, you're exempt, דבעידנא דשדייה מיפסק פסיקי גיריה. Dbe'idna deshadye mifsaq
psiqey girey.
At the time you shot the arrow, these words are a metaphor
but here they're literal, your arrow has already ended. Meaning that arrow
shooting was not an act of murder. It was something that was
going to be neutralized and therefore the act of murder like we
said before is always defined at the moment, not after the fact
looking back. So at that moment that was not an act of
murder. Now even though you had in mind to yank away the-
what do you call it? The shield, that was a different act.
So the act of shooting the arrow was not an act of
murder and the yanking of the- away of the shield is just
taking away something that's protecting the guy. It's not actually holding the
guy in something that is killing him and therefore it's גרמא. grama.
Okay. ואמר רבא,
רבא also says: זרק בו חץ וסמנין בידו. Zarak bo chetz vesamanin
beyado. You shoot an arrow at a guy and the guy's got
you know some type of- type of medicines in his hand that
are going to be able to heal the wound. All right, let's
take an example, maybe make it a little bit more
relatable. The guy's holding on to you know- you- you- you inject
a guy with snake venom but he's holding on to anti-venom and
all he has to do is take it and be fine. Okay,
so- so where are we? ובא אחר ופזרן Uba acher ufizran and
somebody comes and scatters the, you know, knocks the anti-venom out of
his hand. ואפילו הוא קדם ופזרן, Ve'afilu hu kadam ufizran, even the
murderer comes and knocks the anti-venom out of his hand. So פטור,
you're exempt, דבעידנא דשדייה ביה יכול להתרפאות הוה, Dbe'idna deshadye bey yakhol
lehitrapot hava, when the arrow was shot at him or in my
example the venom, he could have healed himself. Now this is a
much bigger חידוש chiddush because the venom or the arrow will kill
the person, right? It's just that he can now go ahead and
heal himself. But- but if he doesn't heal himself, right, this is
the thing actually that will kill. So you would say that's an
act of murder, you know, doing something that has the- that that
thing now on its own left to itself will kill the person.
That- if the guy heals himself, you got saved, you got off
the hook. Obviously only if it kills him is it an act
of murder. But anyway that is actually the thing that is going
to kill the person all on its own without anything else assisting
it, right, it will kill the person, you would say that's an
act of murder. And רבא says no, if the guy who is
being shot at has the ability to heal himself, then in that
context since we assume people will heal themselves, that is not seen
as an act of murder and then afterwards it's just גרמא. Okay.
So now the גמרא says well, if you want to go that
far, says the
גמרא, אמר רב אשי, Rav Ashi הלכך, Hilkhakh, therefore, אפילו סמנין בשוק,
Afilu samanin bashuk, even if he doesn't have the anti-venom but it's
available in the marketplace, since he has access to it and could
get it in time, when you shot the guy, you didn't kill
him because he can just go ahead and fix it himself, go
to the marketplace and buy it, presumably he's got enough money or
whatever. Okay. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא
לרב
אשי, Amar ley Rav Acha brey deRava leRav Ashi, let's- see how
far we can push this. נזדמנו לו סמנין מהו? Nizdamnu lo samanin
mahu? Let's say the guy inserted the venom and the victim didn't
have anti-venom and it wasn't in the marketplace and then before he
died somebody- somebody said wait, wait, I got- got some antivenom and
offered it to him and then he just for whatever reason decided
not to take it. So would you say there that that was
an act of murder? Okay, so it seems to me, yes. At
the moment that that was happening, it was going to kill him,
you know, by some נס neis somebody showed up with antivenom and
for whatever reason he didn't use it. Okay, but at the moment
it was going to kill him and it did kill
him. So אמרי ליה לא הרי יצא מבית דין זכאי, Amrei lei
no harei yatza mibeis din zakai, since for a moment you got,
the murderer got off, as soon as the guy showed up with
the antivenom, this guy now could be saved and that would have
meant that oh, this thing isn't lethal. Okay, so that's enough to
get him off. The fact that something happened before it killed him
that if this person would have acted on it actually could have
saved himself, that means that it's now not an act of murder,
which is pretty, all of this is very, very shocking. It just
shows how narrowly we are defining sort of this act. But that
one I must tell you, even in a formal sense, I don't
really get it. רש"י Rashi says the phrase of יצא מבית דין
זכאי, yatza mibeis din zakai, רש"י Rashi says אין לנו לחיובו מצא
לו זכות, ein lanu lechaivo matza lo zechus,
like it's a way to get him off, you know, the idea
that we're really trying to avoid executing. Okay. ואמר רבא,
now we move from this idea that the act was nothing but
then you did, well not nothing, but whatever, wasn't enough and then
you did something else that made it potent. Now we're going to
get to this question about what defines an act. So we already
had holding the guy under, but now we're going to deal with
like when your energy sort of gets redirected. Let's take a look.
So ואמר רבא זורק צור בכותל וחזר לאחוריה והרג חייב. Ve-amar Rava
zorek tzur bekoshel vechazar le-achoreha veharag chayav. So somebody throws a
rock and he's a really good shot, he's been practicing, and it
rebounds and it kills somebody on the rebound and that was his
intention. So you're חייב, that's still all of your act, your energy
into the rock and continues to propel the rock, okay, and therefore
you're going to be חייב and you intended to do it. Now,
what if rather than throwing against a wall where it's all still
your energy, you know, you well I guess even if you threw
it against like a trampoline or something, it's still your energy, it
just preserves more of it. Right, so all those cases it's still
your energy in the rock and you intended it and you're חייב.
So ותנא תונא, U-tna tuna, we taught similarly in a ברייתא: Beraita:
כגון אלו המשחקים בכדור, kegon eilu hamesachakim bekadur, like people that say
sort of this like a what's that called squash, they throw a
ball on a you know against a wall and want it to
rebound very far. שהרגו במזיד נהרגין, sheharagu be-meizid neheragin, if they did
something like that and killed someone, if it was intentional, נהרגין, neheragin,
then it's an act of murder and they'd be executed. בשוגג גולין,
beshogeg golin,
if it was unintentional, they would be exiled. So the Gemara says
בשוגג גולין פשיטא, beshogeg golin peshita, that's obvious, like by גלות golus
you don't need as much of an intentional act or even as
direct of an act, right? I mean accidentally the top of the
hatchet flies off, right, that's גלות, golus, of course you'd be גלות.
golus. But it says במזיד נהרגין איצטריכא ליה. bemeizid neheragin itztricha lei.
The חידוש chiddush is that it's considered when it's intentional, it's considered
an act of murder. מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought
התראת ספק הוא, hatra'as safek hu,
maybe it's doubtful warning, meaning of course it's כוחו kocho with your
energy, that's not an issue. But I might have thought it's doubtful
warning. מי יימר
דהדרא הוא, mi yeimar d'hadra hu, who said that it's going to
you know come back the way you intend? קא משמע לן kamashma
lan that it's not considered, if this is what the guy's trying
to do and it turns out he did do it and some
people are able, you know, have the skill, so it's not a
ספק, safek, this is exactly what he's trying to do even though
something could always happen to set it off to make it you
know to make to make not do what was intended. Nevertheless, it's
considered, that was the intent and that's what the person had the
ability to do. תני רבי תחליפא בר אמרא קמיה דרבי אבהו, Tani
Rabbi Tachlifa bar Amra kamei d'Rabbi Abbahu, so רבי תחליפא בר אמרא
Rabbi Tachlifa bar Amra taught in front of רבי אבהו: Rabbi Abbahu:
כגון אלו המשחקים בכדור שהרגו תוך ארבע אמות פטור. kegon eilu hamesachakim
bekadur sheharagu toch arba amos patur.
Those who are playing with the ball, if it killed within ארבע
אמות, arba amos, they're פטור. חוץ לארבע אמות חייב, chutz l'arba amos
chayav, more than ארבע אמות, arba amos, it rebounded more than ארבע
אמות, arba amos, they're חייב. So אמרי ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amrei
lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said to רב אשי: Rav
Ashi: היכי דמי, heichi dami,
what's the case? אי דניחא ליה, ei d'nicha lei, if you're trying
to get it within ארבע אמות arba amos and it killed within
ארבע אמות, arba amos, so אפילו פורתא נמי, afilu purta nami, even
less than ארבע אמות arba amos you should be חייב. אי דלא
ניחא ליה, ei d'lo nicha lei, if you're not trying, אפילו טובא
נמי לא, afilu tuva nami lo, even if it goes very far
you should be פטור if it did something you weren't intending. אמר
ליה, amar lei, so he said back to him: סתם משחקים בכדור,
stam mesachakim bekadur, no, no, because the normal cases of people that
are playing with balls, כמה דאזיל טפי, kama d'azil tfei,
the more that it rebounds, ניחא להו, nicha leihu, they more they
want it. Which means what? Which means by default we can assume
he was trying to get it out of ארבע אמות. arba amos.
So if it went within ארבע אמות, arba amos, that was seen
to do not what he was intending. Now, the big question here
is is this talking about intentional murder and getting the death penalty
or unintentional and getting גלות? golus? It's very hard to read it
intentional because if intentional, who cares what normal ball players are trying
to do? This guy was trying to kill the person and he
tried to do it by getting a rebound, so who cares what
normal means norm, most of the time people are only trying to
get it to be more than ד אמות *four amos*. Who the
heck cares? This is what this guy tried and he murdered the
guy. So it seems like we're talking about a case I mean
רש"י ותוספות *Rashi and Tosafot* debate this or discuss it. And they're
bothered either way. It seems like we're talking about a case that
was unintentional. People were playing ball, it was reckless, and it wound
up killing somebody. And then we're saying, oh, so if it was
within ד אמות *four amos*, that clearly was not what they were
trying to do, and therefore they'd be exempt from גלות *Galus*. If
it rebounded as far as they were trying and it accidentally killed
somebody, they're חייב *chayav* in גלות *Galus*. So that all makes sense,
that we're talking about unintentional. The problem is, is that why would
you be exempt from גלות *Galus* even if it did something you
weren't trying to do? The classic case of גלות *Galus* is that
the guy is chopping wood and the head of the hatchet flies
off and kills somebody. That's much more unintentional and that's גלות *Galus*.
So why should the fact that you were trying to get the
ball to rebound ד אמות *four amos* and only rebounded ב אמות
*two amos* be enough to get you off? So that's what תוספות
*Tosafot* discusses here. Really at the end he doesn't know the answer
to that. If you look at the last line of תוספות *Tosafot*,
he says, ומיהו תימא *Umihu teima*, this is
the last of the narrow lines, הא דפליגי רבי ורבנן ברישא לא
גולים בנשמט הברזל מקתו *Ha de'paligi Rebbe ve'Rabbanan be'reisha lo golim be'nishmat
ha'barzel mi'kato*, when the hatchet flies off of the handle, ומן העץ
המתבקע *u'min ha'etz hamitpakeia*, or a, you know, or some splinter comes
flies off of the wood that's being chopped, מר מחייב בהאי ומר
מחייב בהאי *Mar mechayev be'hai u'mar mechayev be'hai*, one way or another
you're חייב *chayav* in one of those scenarios. אמאי חייב האי הוי
כמו נתכוון לזרוק ב וזרק ד *Amai chayav hai havei kemo niskavein
lizrok bet ve'zarak arba*, דמתכוון לבקוע עצים שלפניו והלך למרחוק *demiskavein livkiyot
etzim she'lifanav ve'halach lemerachok*. Okay, so it doesn't really explain why that
case is more חייב *chayav* than when you're trying to have it
rebound a lot and then only rebounds a little. So I don't
know, but anyway when we get to מכות *Makkot* we can worry
more about גלות *Galus*. Let's just go back to the גמרא *Gemara*.
Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says, למימרא דהאי גוונא כוחו הוא *Lemeimra
de'chai gavna kocho hu*. So the
real point here of רבא *Rava's* teaching is that when something rebounds
it's still your energy and you're חייב *chayav* because remember, you need
your physical act or your energy, like if you throw a rock,
that's still your act because your energy is in the rock even
though it's not a part of your body that hits the guy,
or you shoot an arrow. And when it rebounds it's still your
energy. Okay, that's the basic חידוש *chiddush*.
ורמינהו *U'remihu*, I'll ask you on this. המקדש ונפל קידוש על ידו
או על הצד *Ha'mekadesh ve'nafal kiddush al yado o al hatzad*, so
basically when you add the ashes of the פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah*
to the water, that's considered קידוש *kiddush*, you're sanctifying it. And it
has to be added through your act and your energy. Okay, so
let's say you were going and adding those ashes, but it fell
on your hand, it didn't go straight into the water. And then
from your hand it went into the water. Or it hit the
side of the vessel and from there it fell into the water.
ואחר כך נפל לשוקת *Ve'achar kach nafal la'shokat*, and then it fell
into the trough. פסול *Pasul*, it's not a good putting of the
water because it wasn't your energy. Why not? It just rebounded. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says no, הכא במאי עסקינן בשוטת *hacha be'mai askinan
be'shotet*. It didn't bounce off with your initial energy. It hit your
hand and landed on your hand and then it just fell off
by gravity. So that's not your energy and therefore that's why it's
not your placing into the water. תא שמע *Ta shema*, come and
hear. מחט שהיא נתונה על החרס *Machat shehi nesunah al hacheres*, now
let's say you had a needle that was on a piece of
pottery and now you're splashing the ashes of פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah*,
you know, the water with the ashes of the פרה אדומה *Parah
Adumah* on that needle in order to purify the needle. Now you
have to intentionally, you have to, same thing here, when you're purifying,
it needs to be your energy that is causing the water to
hit the thing. So what happened? והזה עליה *Ve'hizah aleha*. So
the water is on top of this needle. ספק על המחט הזה
וספק על החרס הזה ומיצה עליה *Safek al hamachat hizah ve'safek al
hacheres hizah u'mitzah aleha*. You don't know, did the water initially hit
the needle or did it initially hit the pottery and from there
rebound onto the needle? ומיצה להזתו *U'mitzah le'hazato*. פסול *Pasul*, it's invalid.
So I'm saying why is it invalid? As long as it rebounded
it should be your energy, it should be fine. So אמר רב
חיננא בר יהודה משמיה דרב מצה איתמר *amar Rav Chinena bar Yehuda
mishmei de'Rav matza itmar*. It's not that it was מיצה *mitzah*, it
rebounded on it, it was מצה *matza*. You found the water on
the needle. And you don't know how did the water get on
the needle? Did it get on it because it went straight or
if it rebounded, then it would be fine. Or did it get
on it because it landed on the pottery and then slowly, you
know, made its way to the needle? Then it wouldn't be your
energy and then it would be no good. Okay. אמר רב פפא
*Amar Rav Papa*,
one more case for today. האי מאן דכפתיה לחבריה ואתייה לבידקא דמיא
*Hai man de'kaftei le'chaverei ve'atyei le'vidka de'maya*. This is a hugely important
פסק *psak* about deciding in cases of like גרמא *grama* and מעשה
*ma'aseh*. Somebody binds up his friend and puts him right in front
of a dam, and then opens up the dam gates or the
sluice gates or whatever they're called. האי מאן דכפתיה לחבריה ואתייה לבידקא
דמיא *Hai man de'kaftei le'chaverei ve'atyei le'vidka de'maya*. גירי דידיה הוא *Girei
didei hu*. So that,
those are his arrows, meaning even though, even though you are not,
even though you are not actually either shooting and putting your energy
into the thing, which is what we've been talking about now, it's
not your body that's hitting the guy, it's not something that you
put your energy into, you're not holding the guy under the water.
Nevertheless, when you open up the sluice gate, the fact that the
water initially comes out and hits the guy as soon as you
open the gate and you release that power, by releasing that energy,
that is like you put that energy into the water and you
hit and you threw the water on the guy. So that's a
very big חידוש *chiddush*. Okay, so let's read that again. האי מאן
דכפתיה לחבריה ואשקיה בדקא דמיא *Hai man de-kaftiyeh le-chavereih ve-ashkiyeh bi-deka de-maya*.
גירי דידיה הוא *girei dideih hu*. That becomes your arrows, that you
removed the thing, the thing that was holding back the water, that
becomes your arrows, ומחייב *u-mechayav*, and you're liable. Now here's an important
limitation about that. הני מילי בכוח ראשון *Hani mili be-koach rishon*, אבל
בכוח שני גרמא בעלמא הוא *aval be-koach sheni grama be-alma hu*. That's
only if it's the first energy, but the second energy, it's only
indirect causation. What's the difference? Well, first what's the description of the
difference? So רש"י *Rashi* says the description of the difference is, did
you remove it and then immediately it, like the water released and
immediately the first thing that happened is it hit the guy and
it killed him, or is the guy a little bit further away
from where the sluice gates are and when you open it, first
the water hits the bed of the, whatever, the riverbed, and then
it proceeds on? So the water sort of goes in like two
stages. So that's what רש"י *Rashi* says, that already is just you
caused it to happen, but it's obviously there are a lot of
cases, not a precise definition, but somehow the initial releasing of energy,
right, and then the thing happens. A good way to see would
be let's say also you removed a door from under something and
it fell through a trapdoor. That has potential energy in it and
the releasing of that potential energy is like you put the energy
in, and that you made that happen. That's when it happens in
that first sort of hit. But if it happens afterwards then that's
considered to be not yours, that's considered a גרמא *grama*. So one
actually wonders, right, let's say it's a case of this, of a
rebound. Let's say it's not like the thing flowed, let's say the
water hit the ground and then rebounded and with that energy killed
somebody, or the case of the, let's say you had a ball,
right, and you released a trapdoor and it fell down and rebounded
and killed somebody. So if you had thrown it, we just got
through learning that you'd be חייב *chayav*. That rebound is your energy.
Here when you release it, did that become your energy and the
rebound is חייב *chayav*, or no, since you didn't put the energy
in, we're only going to say you're חייב *chayav* if it hits
initially. Anything after that initial moment, even if it's a direct rebound
and it's with that energy, then that type of a case you're
going to be פטור *patur*. So that's not clear. Obviously these are
really core questions of how do you define action, your energy, your
act, an indirect act, and so on. Okay, we will continue with
this tomorrow.